A Guide to the Papers of Notable Virginia Families, 1763-1866
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Madison Family Papers
  - Correspondence
    - Thomas Ritchie (1778-1854), editor of Richmond Enquirer, to James Madison and Dolley Madison 1825 December 10, n.d. (Box 3)
      Fears that the effort to promote a national system of roads and canals, possibly through a constitutional amendment, will violate the Constitution, and sees this tendency in recent speeches of John Quincy Adams.
    - Judith Page Walker Rives to Dolley Madison 1836 July 10 (Box 3)
      Expresses their condolences on the death of James Madison.
    - William Cabell Rives (1792-1868) to James C. McGuire 1857 and 1866 (Box 3)
      Writes concerning his examination of various books, papers and manuscripts of James Madison, E. Randolph, Edmund Pendleton, Joseph Jones, John Witherspoon, with an unidentified note discussing the various wills of Dolley Madison.
    - Asher Robbins (1757-1845) to Dolley Madison 1837 and 1839 (Box 3)
      Sends a copy of his speech and thanks her for her prized note of appreciation.
    - Catherine Eliza (Murray) Rush to Dolley Madison [ca. 1814] (Box 3)
      Regrets being unable to accept a social invitation for her mother because she is upset at the recent events near Annapolis.
    - Elijah Russell to James Madison 1801 June 27 (Box 3)
      Asks Madison to send any material of a public nature to him to be printed in his newspaper The Republican Gazette, Concord, New Hampshire
    - Stephen Sayre (1736-1818) to James Madison 1801 October 21 (Box 3)
      Questions the political appointment of Daniel Ludlow (1750-1814).
    - Maria D. (Mayo) Scott to Dolley Madison 1847 December 23 (Box 3)
      Presents two of her friends from Paris.
    - Fulwar Skipwith (1765-1839) to James Madison 1806 September 3 (Box 3)
      Discusses the shipment of china from Mr. Nast, of Paris, to Madison, in the United States.
    - Elizabeth Scott (Smith) Spencer to Dolley Madison 1842 November 9 (Box 3)
      She is pleased to be able to help Dolley concerning her nephew.
    - George W. Spotswood to John Payne Todd 1841 September 15 (Box 3)
      Rumors about the bad financial condition of the brother of Dolley Madison and his dissipation in Springfield, Illinois.
    - Mrs. Deborah Stabler to Dolley Madison 1842 January 17 (Box 3)
      Remembers the legal assistance of James Madison to her son many years ago and discusses the history of her family over the years since.
    - John Taliaferro to Dolley Madison 1839 January 1 (Box 3)
      Expresses New Year's wishes.
    - Talleyrand (1754-1838) to Robert Livingston 1803 March 22 (Box 3)
      In French, probably from a copy in possession of James Monroe and forwarded to Madison)
    - Hubbard Taylor to James Madison 1801 July 15 and November 16 (Box 3)
      Seeks the office of marshal for the state of Kentucky and offers help in settling matters pertaining to the lands of Madison's father.
    - Richard Taylor (1745-1829) to James Madison 1803 September 12 (Box 3)
      Application for the position of collector at the port of Louisville Falls of Ohio.
    - Littleton Waller Tazewell (1774-1860) Letters concerning the Van Ness Case and William H. Crawford 1823-1834 (Box 3)
      Concurs with the legal opinion of George Hay concerning the Van Ness case and related letters (1823 April 19, 1828 June 14); the presidential election for 1828 and the possible nomination of William H. Crawford (1827 December 22); and certificate signifying John Robinson as clerk of Circuit Superior Court, Henrico County, and William H. Richardson, as Secretary of the Commonwealth.
    - Daniel Triplett to James Madison, Sr. and James Madison, Jr. 1794 and 1801 (Box 3)
      Discusses financial matters and asks help in securing a job with the government.
    - Benjamin Tucker, English engineer, (1762-1829) to Sir Thomas Tyrwhitt (1762-1832) 1820 April 14 (Box 3)
      Describes his visit to the buildings built for the Metropolitan School of Industry at Dartmoor, and found them suitable for the acceptance of at least two thousand children.
    - Delia (Jarvis) Tudor to Dolley Madison 1811 December 27 (Box 3)
      Writes seeking the consulship in London for her son, William Tudor, Jr. (1779-1830).
    - Baron Louis Marie Turreau de Linieres (1756-1816) to James Madison [1805 April 17?] (Box 3)
      Social greeting.
    - John Tyler (1790-1862) to Thomas Ritchie 1853 January 22 (Box 3)
      Discusses the printing of the letter of his wife, Julia Gardiner Tyler, addressing English ladies on the subject of slave emancipation, in Ritchie's newspaper, the Richmond Enquirer, his fears of the expanding role of the Federal government, mentions Franklin Pierce, and the Cuba question.
    - Unknown correspondent to James Madison and James Monroe, concerning quartermaster patronage during the War of 1812 [1814-1815?] (Box 3)
    - John Vaughan to Dolley Madison 1838 March 23 (Box 3)
      Responds to her note and sends a review of the latest book associated with the American Philosophical Society.
    - Jacob Wagner to James Madison 1802 April 30 (Box 3)
      Explains the necessity of leaving the employment of the State Department.
    - John William Wallace (1815-1884) to Dolley Madison 1844-1845 (Box 3)
      Proposes an exchange of letters by the youthful James Madison, in his possession, for letters by his kinsman, William Bradford, in Dolley Madison's possession, associated since their Princeton College days, so a more complete record might be had of both.
    - Thomas Welch to John Payne Todd 1849 January 1 (Box 3)
      Asks him to return the first volume of the Madison papers which he borrowed last winter.
    - Abigail Wildes to Dolley Madison 1810 August (Box 3)
      Sends her thanks for the gift of the gold chain and earrings.
    - Isaac Winston (1772-1867) to James Madison 1801 November 26 (Box 3)
      Asks him about the truth of a rumor that a general peace has been reached in Europe.
    - William Wirt (1772-1834) to Robert Bevridge 1826 April 6 (Box 3)
      Thanks the Society for his election as an honorary member of the St. Andrews Society of Baltimore.
    - William Wirt to Richard S. Coxe (1792-1865) 1829 November 5 (Box 3)
      Sends a power of attorney, and discusses his association with the legal case of Mr. Henderson, for which he was never paid.
  - Manuscripts and Other Madison Papers
    - Autographs of John Dawson, John Robertson, Clement C. Biddle, and unidentified n.d. (Box 3)
    - Biographical Note on James Madison in an unknown hand 1814 December (Box 3)
    - "The Charters of the State of Virginia" and "Virginia's Boundaries" by [James Madison?] (copy) n.d. (Box 3)
    - Deeds conveying slaves and other property from Dolley Madison to John Payne Todd 1844 June 16-July 17 (Box 3)
    - "Description of the Residence of ex-President James Madison," Montpelier, Orange County, Virginia, by Fleming Lipscomb n.d. (Box 3)
    - Draft of James Madison's Second Inaugural Address [1813 March?] (Box 3)
    - Legal Papers, including a bond of William Sharp to John Payne Todd, copy of the agreement between Henry Moncure and Ambrose Madison concerning the sale of Montpelier, indenture between Dolley Madison and Richard D. Cutts, and a petition concerning the revocation of letters of collection concerning the estate of Dolley Madison 1837-1849 (Box 3)
    - List of Books sent to James Madison by Thomas Jefferson from France, in Madison's hand 1790 August (Box 3)
    - List of "Oil Paintings at Montpellier" and List of "Valuables belonging to the Estate of the Late Mrs. D.P. Madison" ca. 1849 (Box 3)
    - List of Silverware purchased in France by James Monroe, with two lines in the hand of James Monroe 1803 July 2 (Box 3)
    - Manuscript Fragment, Page 6, concerning British capture of American ships and impressment [1812?] (Box 4)
    - Manuscript on Money by James Madison (copy) [ca. 1779-1780] (Box 4)
    - "Mr. [Joseph?] Story's idea [as to the Embargo] early in Session" [ca. 1809?] (Box 4)
    - Note concerning a paper on "the question of the power to establish a Bank" prepared by James Madison [ca. 1836] (Box 4)
    - Notes made by Inman Horner, possibly for William Cabell Rives' biography of Madison, concerning a manuscript digest [no longer extant?] made by Madison of William Salkeld's Reports of Cases.n.d. (Box 4)
    - Nullification Manuscript by James Madison (copy) n.d. (Box 4)
    - Papers concerning the rank of General Andrew Jackson in 1814 1823 (Box 4)
    - Patriotic poem by Ebenezer Breed, sent to James Madison and Elbridge Gerry 1814 August (Box 4)
    - Poem entitled "Resignation" by Judge St. George Tucker sent to Dolley Madison n.d. (Box 4)
    - Prospectus for the Writings of James Madison, possibly in the hand of James Madison Cutts, including a memorandum re printing n.d. (Box 4)
    - Recommendation of John Hall Rogers for post of consul at Valencia sent to James Madison [ca. 1801-1809?] (Box 4)
    - "Resolution appointing a committee to wait on Mrs. Madison" by U.S. House of Representatives 1844 January 8 (Box 4)
    - "Substance of a conversation held by James Madison, Jr. with Colonel Beckwith at the desire of Mr. Jefferson" concerning the supply of Northwest Indians with arms [ca. 1791 April 18] (Box 4)
    - Wills of Dolley Madison (drafts) and Notification of its Recording 1841-1850 (Box 4)
    - Will of Dolley Madison 1849 June 11 (Box 4)
- Washington Family Papers
  - John H. Ashton to Judge Bushrod Washington 1823 (Box 4)
    Concerning the estate of George Washington.
  - George Ball to Judge Bushrod Washington 1805 (Box 4)
    Concerning the land in Gloucester County belonging to the estate of George Washington, which he contracted to purchase but could not pay.
  - Henry Banks to Judge Bushrod Washington 1823 January 24 (Box 4)
    Sends a contract for land in Kentucky by General M.D. Hardin.
  - Burwell Bassett (1800-1878), guardian to Major George A. Washington's children, to Judge Bushrod Washington 1804-1810 (Box 4)
    Concerning the estate of George Washington, including the division of the western lands, the contract between Washington and George Ball, and his account as guardian.
  - John James Beckley to Edmund Randolph [1783 June 30] (Box 4)
    News of legislative proceedings in the Virginia General Assembly, including paying the principal and interest of the Army debt in eight years, beginning in 1785, and an import duties bill to fund domestic debt.
  - Joseph Biddle to William A. Washington 1804 November 24 (Box 4)
    Refers to business matters.
  - Charles Blackburn, steward of Washington land in Westmoreland County, to William A. Washington 1805-1806 (Box 4)
    Concerning General Henry Lee and his inability or unwillingness to pay his debt to Washington, and his intentions concerning Boyd's land, and other financial matters.
  - William Brent to Judge Bushrod Washington 1826 June 7 (Box 4)
    Discusses the report of George C. Washington concerning his actions with the estate of George Washington.
  - Robert Brooke to William A. Washington 1792 April 3 (Box 4)
    Concerning the estate of Thomas Turner.
  - William Brooke to William A. Washington 1810 January 10 (Box 4)
    Concerning the land of Henry Lee offered to Washington.
  - Reuben Bullard to William A. Washington 1790-1794 (Box 4)
    Concerning his claim against the estate of Richard Henry Lee.
  - Lawrence Butler to William A. Washington 1806-1807 (Box 4)
    Concerning taxes on his Kentucky lands.
  - Gustavus B. Campbell to Corbin Washington 1797 July 15 (Box 4)
  - James Cheston to William A. Washington 1799 March 4 (Box 4)
    Sends a copy of Washington's account with the interest due.
  - James Cox, merchant of Baltimore, Maryland - Business Correspondence 1814-1817 (Box 4)
    Letters are totally concerned with business matters, including accounts, orders, creditors and debtors, and payments.
  - Richard Crampkins to William A. Washington 1804 February 3 (Box 4)
    Discusses the purchase of hay.
  - W. Croghan to Lawrence Butler and James Nivison (copies) 1787, 1802 (Box 4)
    Discusses the need for surveying of "Captain William Saunders military lands".
  - Edward Digges to Corbin Washington 1798 July 17 (Box 4)
    Concerning the estate of Richard Henry Lee.
  - P. Doddridge to Judge Bushrod Washington 1823 December 3 (Box 4)
    His recent illness has prevented him from being well acquainted with the suit that Washington wrote him about.
  - Thomas Evans to Thomas Turner 1774 June 19 (Box 4)
    Pertaining to the settlement of the Thomas Turner estate by William A. Washington?.
  - McCarty Fitzhugh to William A. Washington 1806 (Box 4)
    Concerning the purchase of an estate from General [Henry?] Lee and the payment of a debt to Washington.
  - Philip Fitzhugh to William A. Washington 1797 October 25 (Box 4)
    Request for a deed for land near Baltimore sold to General Lee by Washington.
  - William Fitzhugh to William A. Washington 1808 August 31 (Box 4)
    Remembers that General Washington had told him the tickets were sold by Thompson Mason without the permission of the company but declines to participate in the law suit because of his weakened health.
  - Joseph Forrest to William A. Washington 1806 June 20 (Box 4)
    Discusses Washington's account.
  - John Goulding to William A. Washington 1804 March 24 (Box 4)
    Sends Washington a copy of his account.
  - John Gray to William A. Washington 1797 April 13 (Box 4)
    Requests an order on General Henry Lee.
  - Marsh Hardin to William A. Washington 1807 February 7 (Box 4)
    Enclosed two patents for land (not present) to William Saunders, which Washington notes was not by his direction or knowledge.
  - Henry Hiort to William A. Washington 1800 May 8 (Box 4)
    Mentions the deed for the Berkeley land of [General Henry Lee?.
  - George Hoffman to William A. Washington n.d. (Box 4)
    Discusses Mrs. Washington's order for furniture.
  - William Holburne to William A. Washington 1800-1801 (Box 4)
    Writes concerning the evaluation by Colonel John Tayloe of a slave, Sarah, and her three children, sold to Washington (1800 June 29); and his account with Tayloe (1801 April 29).
  - Geb Hollingsworth to William A. Washington 1792 July 17 (Box 4)
    Concerning his wish to be appointed United States district attorney for Baltimore and refers to Washington's marriage to Mary Lee (1764-1795).
  - Jesse Hollingsworth to William A. Washington 1797-1800 (Box 4)
    Asks for him to settle his account which has been past due for five years.
  - Alexander Johnston to William A. Washington n.d. (Box 4)
    Concerning payment on his account with Johnston.
  - Dr. Walter Jones to William A. Washington 1802 November 4 (Box 4)
    Sends his account for payment.
  - Peter Kemp to Corbin Washington 1797-1798 (Box 4)
    Concerning an inventory of Arthur Lee's estate (1797) and the estate of Richard Henry Lee (1798).
  - Thomas Landford to William A. Washington 1807 January 12 (Box 4)
    Recommends William Fox, clerk of Pulaski County, as a man of candor and integrity, who can be trusted to render a just evaluation of the lands in his Washington's contract with Colonel Jesse Richardson.
  - Fielding Lewis to Judge Bushrod Washington 1821-1822 (Box 4)
    Concerning Washington's dividend from the Dismal Swamp Canal Company and the difficulties that a drought produced in transporting the lumber and shingles manufactured by the company.
  - Lawrence Lewis to Judge Bushrod Washington ca. 1802-1820 (Box 4)
    Concerning the estate of General Washington after the death of Martha Washington.
  - Robert Lewis to William A. Washington 1804-1823 (Box 4)
    Concerning the will and estate of General Washington after the death of Martha Washington, especially the Ashby's Bent tract and the Chatten's run tract (1804 January 8); the suit against Samuel Washington (1808 January 20); and mentions widespread illness in Fredericksburg (1823 September 8).
  - John McIver to William A. Washington 1805-1807 (Box 4)
    Concerning grants of land to Washington, including the comments of Colonel Richardson, of Pulaski County, Kentucky, concerning two surveys of land on Buck's Creek, [Pulaski County?], the survey of land on Little River, Christian County, Kentucky, his claim on the south side of Tennessee which interferes with the Indian claim, and difficulties with his patent issued in the name of William Saunders (see also W. Croghan).
  - Archibald McLean to Judge Bushrod Washington 1824 (Box 4)
    Discusses their law suit and the opinion of Mr. P. Doddridge about the case.
  - George Mason to Judge Bushrod Washington 1825 May 30 (Box 4)
    Mentions seeds sent to the Mount Vernon gardener, including some of the shrub Missouri Honeymeade, brought back from Missouri by Lewis and Clark, and a vine from Chili, in the past, and sends additional plants and the gift of a fishing net and directions for its use, and asks the gardener at Mount Vernon to bud for him a few lemons.
  - Fontaine Maury (1761-1824) to William A. Washington 1796-1799 (Box 4)
    Claims against the estate of Richard Henry Lee.
  - Philip Mazzei Memorandum for Colonel Humphreys [1785-1786] (Box 4)
    Concerning the account of Arn[old?] Henry Dohrman of Richmond, Virginia, and negotiations with Lisbon merchants handled by Mazzei for Congress.
  - Robert Morris to Judge Bushrod Washington 1814 September 28 (Box 4)
    Does not believe that the absence of Washingon from the Trenton, New Jersey, court will cause any injury to his business.
  - John Murphy to Corbin Washington 1796 February 3 (Box 4)
    Encloses Mr. Warden's letter and John Monroe's order.
  - Hudson Muse furnishes a recommendation for Thomas Jesse as overseer 1794 October 25 (Box 4)
  - Nicolson and Heth to William A. Washington 1805 October 11 (Box 4)
    Concerning a shipment of coal.
  - John Payne to William A. Washington 1794 June 17 (Box 4)
    Concerning cash due him for his wheat.
  - Zachariah Poulson, office of The American Daily Advertiser, to Judge Bushrod Washington 1825 August 26 (Box 4)
    Encloses his certificate and account.
  - Jesse Richardson to William A. Washington 1806-1808 (Box 4)
    Writes concerning the delivery of three horses (1806 March 19); their land contract (1806 August 28, December 2; 1808 February 10); bay horses (1807 April 13).
  - Joshua Riddle to William A. Washington 1806 September 12 (Box 4)
    Asks Washington to pay his account.
  - John Ryburn to William A. Washington 1795 March 20 (Box 4)
    Writes concerning Washington's account.
  - Alexander Spotswood to Judge Bushrod Washington 1802-1807 (Box 4)
    Discusses land plats and other business matters, including the estate and guardianship of Bernard Moore (see 1806 March 14); and the Ashby's Bent tract of land (1806 March 14, June 11, July 9, October 29; 1807 January 24, August 7).
  - James Stephenson to William A. Washington 1809 December 26 (Box 4)
    Encloses a letter from Colonel E. McCarty (not present) concerning the quality of some lands conveyed to Washington by General Lee in Hampshire, Virginia.
  - John Stith to William A. Washington 1800 June 14 (Box 4)
    Encloses an order (not present) on Washington from John H. Washington paid by a draft on Mr. Washington of Mount Vernon.
  - W. Stubbs to William A. Washington 1785 March 4 (Box 4)
    Has not yet been able to secure any money from Mr. Booth on his account with Washington.
  - C. Swan to William A. Washington 1805 November 10 (Box 4)
    Although he did purchase coal from Charles Wayman in August, he has both the bill and receipt proving payment.
  - W. Thippen to William A. Washington [1787?] May 15 (Box 4)
    Asks him to pay twenty dollars on his account with General Lee.
  - Jane Thornton to her brother, William A. Washington 1805 November 2 (Box 4)
    Writes concerning the poor health of her husband, tells him about an advertisement informing men who had served in the Virginia Blues under General George Washington, of lands available for them on the Ohio River, and the death of her husband's sister.
  - David Wardrobe to Corbin Washington 1796 September 18 (Box 4)
    Writes concerning a bed belonging to the Richard Henry Lee estate.
  - George Steptoe Washington to Judge Bushrod Washington 1803-1805 (Box 4)
    Writes concerning lands involved in the estate of General Washington after the death of Martha Washington, particularly the boundaries to be conveyed to Parks and Lee (1805 January 10).
  - William A. Washington to Lawrence Lewis 1806 September 5 (Box 4)
    Fees paid on the estate of George Washington.
  - William Wirt to Judge Bushrod Washington 1825 July 2 (Box 4)
    Asks Washington's help in disputing a statement by Governor G.M. Troup before the Georgia legislature about the abolition of slavery supposedly made by William Wirt before the Supreme Court, specifically "that slavery, being inconsistent with the laws of God and nature, cannot exist".
  - Thomas C. Wright to William A. Washington 1808 April 30 (Box 4)
    Writes concerning the account of Colonel Matthew Lyon (1750-1822) of Kentucky.
  - Financial and Legal Documents, including: receipt to William A. Washington from Bushrod Washington (1780); William A. Washington's bond to Richard Henry Lee for the Estate of Arthur Lee (1793); receipts concerning the estate of Richard Henry Lee (1795-1797); account of James Anderson, George Washington's manager and distiller (1799 October); bank receipt of Martha Washington (1802 February 9); receipts concerning the estate of George Washington (1803-1808); the Buck Creek land in Kentucky (1806 March 27; 1807 October 4); and the lawsuit between Michael Cresap and Archibald McLean (1823 July 31) 1780-1823 (Box 4)
  - Land Grant in Harrison County, [West] Virginia, to Dr. Thomas Bond by Patrick Henry, as Governor 1786 July 15 (Box Oversize Folder (Oversize Box X-1))